If I said to you,
'The weather is terrible today,'
what would you expect to see
when you looked out the window?
Um ... fog?
Hail?
Drizzle?
A tornado?
You wouldn't know,
would you?
I was far too vague.
Not only are you none the wiser,
I have almost no control
over what you imagine.
But if I said
'It's pouring with rain out there,'
I've put a much more exact image
in your head.
You know what you're going to see
beyond the curtains.
I might even say
something more exact,
like,
'It's rained 30 inches in the last 24 hours.'
Or
'The house is now entirely submerged in water.
We have to move.'
The same thing applies
when you're writing.
It's easy to fall into
the trap of vagueness,
but if you want to make an impact
with your writing,
you need to be specific.
Being vague means your reader has
to interpret or guess at the details
or what it all means.
And you know what?
They might not even bother.
You have to make the view clear.
So don't write simply,
'Spending on stationery
has increased recently.'
An increase could mean 1% or 1,000%.
It's so vague
it's almost meaningless.
But write,
'Spending on stationery
doubled in the last year,'
and it's clear to everyone.
And look out for words
that seem to promise significance
but actually leave your reader guessing.
When you use these words,
make sure you fill in the gaps.
It could lead you to say
something truly significant.
Something like,
'Spending on stationery
doubled in the last year.
That increase is enough
to finally hire a new sales
manager.'
So always think about the view you're
creating for your reader,
and make
sure you've given them everything
they need to see exactly what you want them to.